>> Good morning.
It is fantastic to be back in
San Francisco build.
It is always fun to be a
developer conference to see
great change.
Developer conferences are always
about understanding tech shifts
and understanding the new stack.
It is also about really coming
to grips with the new
opportunity for us as
developers, for the companies we
work at as well as the broader
world.
Today we are going to unpack
this.
This conference is all about
that.
If there is one key take away it
would be this, how do you all
participate fully in this
frontier intelligence ecosystem.
It is not about any one piece of
technology you hear about or
even the platform itself, it is
about the value that you can
build, you can compound, you can
create on top of the platform.
That's what the conference will
be about and that's what we will
focus on.
Let's take a look at this AI
stack this conference is going
to unpack in a great amount of
detail.
It starts with ubiquitous
compute fabric that expands the
edge and the cloud.
You then have this layer which
is the emerging layer where you
have the models, you have
context, you have the tools, the
models can access, and then you
have the run time where you
deploy the agents and
applications that you build on
top of the content player and
model layer.
Of course you have the best
tooling to do all of this and
you have the security and
compliance and governance.
That's the simplest form.
Let's start where it all starts
which is infrastructure.
In fact let's start at the edge
with windows.
The amount of compute there is,
at the edge is actually
astounding.
Think about every NPU, GPU, CPU
even, every PC
we ask ourselves one simple
question.
Can we do that with this era of
AI.
In some sense we are delivering
that already.
When you look at something like
outlook summarized it is using
on board AI locally.
Same thing with PowerPoint all
text.
Or teams super resolution.
It is just not Microsoft.
It is Adobe effects or premier.
Using windows ML in order to
happen to all of this compute
power is to expand the scope of
windows ML and windows AI.
You now are full install base of
GPUs you can get to.
I am thrilled every developer
out there can count on building
for local on board AI and then
have it run across all of the
install base.
Now if you are -- we are also
announcing two cool models that
are all going to run on windows
in INVOX.
Eye on instruct, it is a great
reasoning model.
We have the planning model eye
-- Ion plan.
You have a full local agentic
loop you can give it tools
access and build a fully agentic
applications without having to
run trip to the cloud.
In order to really push the
limits, realize this unmetered
intelligence, there is a lot of
hardware that we are adding too.
We are thrilled to see the
innovation through the
ecosystem.
The stuff from Intel is exciting
to see.
Qualcomm announced two sets of
things which are great one on
the high end snap dragon X on
the lower end to sub 500PCs.
Of course that brings us to inn
NVIDIA.
This is next generation SOC for
PCs.
It brings together the CPU the
GPU as well as AI capabilities
into a single SOC.
It includes unified memory,
architecture and also integrated
DRTM.
You have the SOC coming
together.
One we build is the Surface
Ultra it is a beautiful device.
It brings the power of inn
NVIDIA together with the design
and Craftsman ship of Surface,
128 giga bites of unified
memory.
Beautiful 2,000 display, and it
has an all day battery life.
Excited to see this later in the
fall.
It is wonderful to see all of
the designs from all of the OEM
partners building and taking
advantage of the SOC and the new
platform and bringing out pretty
exciting machines that are going
to be all available come this
fall.
So, of course, we said, okay,
this is fantastic.
What can we do next?
We said, let's try and push
this.
Push the architecture to its
limit for developers.
What if we could just Max the
compute, Max the memory, build
out that developer machine that
is the dream machine, and that's
what we are announcing today.
Surface RTX, dev VOX.
Let's roll the video.
[Music]
>> It is truly a dream machine.
It has 1 Peta flop of AI
compute.
20CPU cores.
All of those things have 128
giga bites of unified memory
access.
So super excited.
I am on the wait list as well,
there's a wait list.
We will get there.
[Laughter]
So then we said why stop there?
We said what if we did one more
thing?
In fact I think Jensen did that
already.
He said windows is coming to the
DGX station.
I describe it as the desktop
data center which you can have
running a 1 trillion model
locally.
It is close to what we perhaps
had when we built GPT-5 or 3 one
of the first super computers.
It is crazy to think we have
come this far with  where you
can have a data center on your
desktop.
We are extending the developer
end points to the cloud.
Windows 365 has the developer
distribution that is optimized
for developer productivity in
the cloud that's windows 365
that I use every day.
It is about making windows
whether it is on the laptop,
desktop, the cloud wherever the
best place to build.
And so to that end we have tons
and tons of updates.
We have starting  -- we are
starting with the favorite
things for all of us, which is
distraction 3 dev environment.
We are introducing an
intelligent terminal that has
built in GitHub Copilot.
Copilot intelligence.
Of course lots and lots of Linux
love for windows now.
You have 70 plus utilities.
Grab in full glory is now
available for regular windows
access.
70 plus utilities as I said.
All of that is coming to
windows.
We are also bringing that you
love.
Home brew will be on native as
well.
Switching all of this.
Having first class support for
containers while  will hp  --
will really help us when
developing locally.
Showing you all of this on new
surface on RTX.
I wanted to invite up on stage
Kayla to take a spin through all
of the Dev tools.
Kayla, go ahead.
[Applause]
>> Our team has been working
hard to make Windows a great
place for development.
Today I am going to show you
major improvements and
delighters you can try out
today.
What we have here is the default
experience on the Surface RTX
Spark DevBox.
It is calm.
No news feed no widgets popping
up no notifications.
We are in dark mode of course.
I am ready to start development.
There's one thing I would like
to change.
I like to put my task bar on the
left.
Let me jump into my task bar
settings using run which is
built with power tools xand
pallet.
No I want it all of the way on
the left.
There we go.
After popular demand we are
excited to announce vertical
task bar is available in Windows
insider build.
The new surfaSurface RTX Spark
bunch of tools already installed
like python and node.
All developer goodness all in
one file.
If you want the same experience
on your device we are making
this file available to everyone
right now.
We have a public repo set up
with configuration file and how
to apply it.
It will make adjustments to
windows and install all of the
tools.
One cool thing I have running
here is power toys new utility
called grab and move.
Hold ality and move the window
around from anywhere.
You can enable end task which
let's you end the process
without having to open task
manager.
Let me jump into my Dev drive.
It runs with defender running in
async and authorize performance
when comes to developer
scenarios.
Get aware.
We have stuff like last name
change message status of each
file and the branch name is on
the bottom left.
So now let's get started
building and open our terminal.
It helps working with agents
even more seamless.
When you install intelligent
terminal you can pick your
favorite agent.
I am using GitHub Copilot today.
You can use which ever agent
speaks to you.
In intelligent terminal I have
terminal pane at the top and
agent working on the bottom.
I, work between them while the
agent helps along the way.
Here is an air being generated.
Agent pain is able to detect it
and provide a fix which is great
when I don't understand the sin
tax.
I am working on open claw I have
worked it using WSL container.
It is a native container
experience on Windows plus it
can leverage the GPU.
It can reference your existing
container files just like the
one in open claw project.
This is open in Microsoft edit
got sin tax highlighting and
latest version.
You can see the container
running with container command.
Since we are on the topic of WSL
there is a profile that is
comfortable for those using
tools like star, CSH and home
brew.
It has all of the favorite
utilities and available in the
repo I showed earlier and
includes B top one of my
favorites.
The Surface RTX Spark serves
large local models for coding.
I have done development with 120
billion parameter model which
most machines can't load.
We can see how many tokens I
have used locally.
3.4 million tokens leveraged on
the device itself.
We can kickoff agents using
fleet.
Just so you don't have to watch
me type I am going to use
Copilot voice feature which is
leveraging its own local model.
I will hold face for it and tell
it what I want it to do.
Find any console dot right line
calls in the tray and node
projects and convert them to the
standard logger used elsewhere
in the code base.
There we go.
The main agent will delegate sub
agent tasks of appropriate
complexity to the local model
use liesing GPU and making it
cost efficient.
As developers while debugging we
are looking through log files to
diagnose any issues.
Finding the location of the log
files is a challenge.
I would love to be able to type
something like grep log and find
them all.
Sweet.
On top of already adding curl,
car and pseudo to windows now we
are adding over 75 command line
utilities like end, be head,
tail and touch for those of us
who love to live in the
terminal.
So I found all of my log files,
but now having to pars them is
the second challenge.
I have had eye on instruct
practically performing analyses
on my log files this whole time.
Now I can quickly diagnose
anything that has gone wrong in
my development, plus I don't
have to worry about token usage
since it is all local.
We can take a look at the
machinery sources.
Models are loaded you can see 90
gigs of ram being utilized by
the GPU using the full power of
RTX Spark.
We were able to use them
simultaneously unmetered going
through the dev flow without a
hitch.
That's huge.
[Applause]
So I know you are going to love
what the team has been working
on.
We hope it gives you a glimpse
of what's possible on windows
today and where we are headed
next.
Thank you.
Back to you Satya.
>> That's the beginning of
unmetered intelligence having
the models and agents using the
models work in parallel to what
you are doing in the cloud.
That's what the platform enables
as first class.
Let's move to the cloud.
The driving equation for us
remains the same, which is
tokens per dollar per watt.
How do we optimize around this?
When we think about the systems
problem we think about electrons
coming on one end and tokens on
the other end and how do we
think about the systems
optimization end-to-end.
It starts with the data center
design itself.
The core compute, storage,
network.
All of the accelerators that are
going to accelerate each of the
components.
How do you think about the DC to
DC connectivity and networking
as well as the off load to
something like the local
compute.
That's the sort of systems
challenge.
But before we even get into all
of the systems and the
technology and the innovation,
perhaps the most important
design criteria for us is how do
we earn the permission from the
communities in which we are
building these data centers.
That's where these principles
ground us and focus us.
How do we ensure that the DCs do
not increase the electro city
prices.
Making sure we are using water
use.
Creating jobs for the local
residents.
Adding to the tax base.
Making sure we are strengthening
communities by investing in had
local training and the
nonprofits in the area.
Only when we live up to the
principles do the hard work is
when we innovate and build.
We have been doing a lot of data
center build up.
Today Azure spans more than 500
data centers in the region.
We have the most expansive
hyperscaler footprint out there.
We have added more data center
capacity in the last 18 months
than the first decade of to put
that in perspective.
We built out the cloud
infrastructure for hetero genius
workloads that span the
enterprise.
When you look at what we are
building when you think of all
of the gigawatts that are going
to come on-line we have three
dominant workloads.
There is training, inference and
the agent run time.
These are three dominant
workloads.
In fact when you look at fair
water it was sort of our first
AI super factory.
It spanned two regions, Georgia
and Wisconsin.
The entire system was designed
from the ground up for AI.
We worked in fact very closely
with inn NVIDIA on this.
It is a two-story architecture
that lets us he goes --
essentially put the number of
GPU densely with network access.
Means you really got fantastic
higher performance networking,
lower latency and more band
width across the entire cluster.
We are rethinking even the power
delivery.
Pou do  -- how do we deliver 100
kilowatts her row with the
conversion loss to the grid to
silicon.
We took a new approach to it.
Also changes with the cooling
system and water.
The tooling loop is filled and
the data center can operate
effectively with zero water
consumption.
The daily water usage over the
course of the entire one year is
equivalent to what the single
restaurant would use.
[Applause]
When it comes to the systems in
the silicon, we have a lot of
choice.
We have first party silicon, we
have partner systems.
We have the first cloud to bring
up inn  NVIDIA.
We work close with AMD.
Working with them on the NX
generation AMD GPU.
Meyer 200 is continuing to scale
it is live in Arizona will
deploy internationally.
It delivers 30% per tokens per
dollar verses what's is the
leading GPU today.
We have validated it with GPD55
and we are going to use that to
power Microsoft 365 Copilot.
When it comes to running these
agents, interesting thing now it
is no longer about having AI
accelerator or GPU.
CPU is critical.
Ratios may be coming to one is
to one.
That's why we are innovating
with cobalt.
We are announcing preview Of
Co
Cobalt00VMs.
Next generation on generation
CPU designed for cloud native
and agent workloads today.
It is exciting to see Cobalt
make progress as well.
[Applause]
One thing we are trying to make
sure being optimized for the new
agent workloads.
Cobalt delivers 30% better than
Cobalt on cloud native.
Using GitHub Copilot traces
these agentic traces to see.
The call patterns are so
different.
We are seeing 33% lower latency
for the agent calls, 14% faster
speed, 23% higher through put.
This is about the co design of
both the AI accelerator and the
CPU for the agent.
And of course, when you talk
about AI workloads you need
scale, you need reliability and
that's why the network becomes
super critical.
We have innovated with the
architecture and rebuilt how
traffic across Azure moves to
support workloads which is
synchronous data workloads.
They span 10s of thousands of
GPUs.
You need to have them coherent.
That's what the next frontier is
to make sure we are able to keep
scaling the network
architarchi
architecture.
It is not just about outside it
is inside the data centers.
It is connected through our
continent spanning AI with the
truly fungible compute fabric.
All of this innovation is
exciting, but when you think
about innovation designing for
AI and I would say deep
understanding of systems,
there's no better company than
NVIDIA and there's no other
person than Jensen to talk about
it.
I want to invite Jensen Wang
from NVIDIA.
I know it is late for you in
Taipei.
I appreciate you staying up.
I have been looking at social
and people talking about your
keynote.
The concept of unmetered
intelligence right at the edge
is so hot again.
You have thought about this,
talked about this, now of course
with RTX Spark really delivered
what is a break through system
for AI to be much Moreau  --
more ubiquitous.
Maybe you can share where you
see this going?
>> It all started about three
years ago with a conversation
between you and I.
We were talking about how we
could build a new class of PCs
incredible for designers and
creators and it would be
incredible for artificial
intelligence.
It would be one of these systems
that has the processing
capability but also the software
stack that is integrated into
the world's design packages and
creator packages and all of the
things we are doing with AI.
Here we are three years later we
built an incredible new chip,
and this system is supported by
all of this new software you
created for Windows.
We have autonomous agent running
on the PC.
When you step back and think
about what does that mean?
For 40 years or some 30 years we
have been working together we
went from inventing direct X
together to creating now this
incredible computer that has
autonomous systems running.
The PC evolved from being an
incredible tool to now being a
tool that is used autonomously
by an AI assistant.
The idea I could be traveling
and on the phone and text my PC
and ask my PC to get coding done
or an idea I have and it would
fire up the tools on the PC and
it would make the modifications
or the changes or the design
that I told it to do, and it
would iterate with me while I am
away from the PC.
My PC became an assistant.
While I am sitting there it
would my great system as well.
The idea that the PC evolved
from a personal computer to
personal AI is really exciting.
To see it come to life and
actually doing that, I am super
excited about it.
Spark you mentioned earlier has
all of these capabilities Peta
flop of AI performance.
Has a Peta flop of MVFP4
numerical format our companies
worked on together that allows
it to take advantage of the 128
giga bites of memory and fit
maybe a couple hundred billion
parameter model.
A couple hundred billion
parameter model is state of the
art.
The days of having a really
smart assistant running on the
PC is here.
>> It is awesome.
I am excited about Windows
coming to the GP300.
It is a data center on your
laptop.
Talking about the data center
side.
This entire thing got started
when we built the first super
computer to train the GPU
models.
I was talking about the fair
water design, this custom build
for the grace black water era to
Max the data center design with
the system design you had.
Now of course we are validating
be
belly --.
Maybe you can share on the clout
side how you are sharing the
system.
>> Our journey is incredible.
We built the first AI super
computer together.
Hopper was an incredible
success.
The first two generations were
focused on free training.
Grace Blackwell came along and
all of the focus moved to post
training, reinforcement learning
which allowed us to have
reasoning models.
These reasoning models based on
mixture of experts were
incredibly intelligent, energy
efficient.
It requires giant systems.
We required MV length 72.
The entire rack became one
computer.
We had evolved from one node to
now one rack.
Well, Microsoft deployed the
largest number of grace
Blackwells in the world today.
Largest number of grace
Blackwells in the world.
Fair water is a magnificent
system to look at.
It is an incredible feet.
It is liquid cooled.
Something you mentioned it is
close looped, basically uses
almost no water.
It is incredibly environmentally
friendly energy efficient.
We are able to increase the
token generation rate and reduce
the cost of token generation by
an order of magnitude, some 30
times over hopper.
That was a huge achievement.
Vera Ruben was created for a
world where these AIs are now
agentic.
As hopper was created for
pretraining grace Blackwell for
training, post training and also
inference.
Vera Rubin is designed to run
for agents.
It is the same computing pattern
when run on the RTX Spark.
It is the same agentic system
but of course larger win process
enormous number of them.
Many will be from different
customers and different
partners.
The entire path, coding path
from storage which is the
long-term memory, working memory
is encrypted.
The data is encrypted in transit
and data also incen crepted in
encrypted in use.
This entire disaggregated
distributed computing system you
mentioned CPU Vera is a CPU
designed for agents.
In the past CPUs were designed
for humans.
We are more parent than agents
are.
Agents want low latency.
Vera was designed for extremely
low latency.
Vera Rubin I can't wait to show
everybody.
You stood it up.
Our two teams have been working
closely.
Long before the chips taped out
long before the systems brought
up the two teams were almost
completely aligned.
Data centers created for Vera
Rubin.
It is into the networking and
stack and community.
The moment systems were rolling
off the lines they were building
stood up at Microsoft.
So incredibly excited about the
collaboration.
>> This speed of light execution
for the teams are fantastic to
see.
All of this is to power the
ecosystem around us.
You and I having grown-up with a
PC the server and now with AI,
have always thought about
ultimately it is about creating
the opportunity for every
developer, every organization to
build on the work that we do and
the platforms we create.
Speaking of that there's a lot
of software that vid NVIDIA
builds we will have the models
in foundry, tooling in foundry.
Software will help us with
accelerating our workloads when
it comes to the data warehouse.
We will have the stuff in
windows.
Talk about the broader vision of
what does it mean as an
opportunity.
Everybody talks about the one
model and one piece of tech.
It is about the broadest biggest
opportunity maybe you want to
share a little bit about that.
>> We have been preparing for
this moment.
What happened the last several
months we have been working a
decade and a half together
getting ready for really what
happened in the last several
months.
All of a sudden because of
agentic systems the convergence
of these great models AI is now
useful.
If you look at GitHub, the
commits into GitHub has gone
completely parabolic.
In the last several months the
number of commits increase by a
factor of three.
It is clear agentic systems are
useful, it is doing productive
work and also it is profitable
as a result.
The amount of command for
compute between the usage of AI
the contribution necessary for
agents it has gone through the
roof.
One thing we have been doing
together is making sure all of
the tools agents are using are
fully accelerated.
Fabric is fully accelerated.
We are accelerating data
processing, SQL, Spark, semantic
based, graph based we are going
to make sure all of the tools
available on Azure are going to
be fully GPU accelerated because
the agents are going to be
impa
impatient.
The faster it can iterate and
generate tokens which are
ultimately what the developers
both customers would like to do
is generate a lot of tokens that
are profitable and highly
intelligent.
>> Thank you so much for the
partnership and leadership and
innovation that you bring to
this entire ecosystem and really
thrilled to be working closely
with you and the team and bring
all of this to the developers
here and beyond and look forward
to seeing what the next sort of
few months and the next year
will bring in terns of the
innovation that gets built on
top of the platform.
Thank you again for joining this
late in the night from Taipei.
>> Thank you so much Satya for
your partnership and friendship.
[Applause]
>> So so far we have talked
about the edge and the cloud.
The form factors, when I saw
that Jensen picture from the
weekend where he had all of the
desktops.
I felt man I am back in the 90s.
It is so tool to see the lineup
of all of the machines that I
loved and grew up with back yet
again with new functionality.
The same form factor, but
unbelievable new functionality,
because of the on board AI
capability.
That is sort of what we have
seen with the laptop, the
desktop and of course with the
cloud.
But it also, you know, sets up
that next question.
If you have that capability,
which is new function and you
can put it into existing form
fac
factors, can you even purpose
build new form factors for the
new function?
Can you build a new platform
even for the agent era?
And that is the motivation
behind project Solara.
I wanted to invite Stevie on
stage but first let's roll the
video.
>> First there's you.
Then everything in front of you.
We get it.
The noise, the weight of it all.
We have been building something.
For an agent first world.
New agent first devices.
You come close, it is ready when
you are.
You speak, it understands you.
What matters comes forward.
Everything else falls away.
When you want it to keep going
it keeps going.
Sometimes it sits with you.
Sometimes it goes with you.
Sometimes it sees what you want
it to see.
It doesn't decide for you.
It lights the path.
Tries to clear the way when you
need it to.
That's the idea.
A whole ecosystem built to clear
the way.
Wherever you are, whenever it
matters.
>> I am so excited to be here.
It really is great to be back on
this stage.
Before I talk about those
awesome new devices you just
saw, let me start with the why.
Back at build 2023 I talked
about the outside AI
infrastructure.
It moves within the application
frame to operating globally to
connect maintain context across
entire workflows, devices and
time scales.
What if there were an ecosystem
of devices specifically designed
for the new type of application
structure for those types of
agents for that transaction.
That's the impetus behind
project Solara.
With many possible forms which
one do you pick?
What is the next device.
The big uh-huh for us is that it
is not choosing one form factor
it is about creating a system
that extends your agent across a
cons  constellation of devices.
The next computer is all of the
devices working together as one
system with agents cloeing up
closer to where and when you
need them.
To realize this vision two
challenges immediately show up.
First many specialized form
factors already exist but often
rely on custom one off apps and
fragmented stacks that are
difficult and expensive to
build, deploy and maintain.
Second across every industry
people and organizations are
already building their own
agents deeply specialized and
instrumented for their work.
The impact of those agents is
constrained by how and where
they can exist.
Project Solara does both by
extending agents on to new
purpose built easy to manage
form factors designed to reach
the nooks and crannies where
project creators do not exist or
are not optimal.
It is a turnkey solution for
building unique agent first
devices enabled by three
pillars.
First it is enterprise ready.
Enabled by the AOSP based
Microsoft device ecosystem
platform.
Second it has an agent driven
interaction model with just in
time UI that adapts to the form
factor.
Third it has extensibility so
you can bring your own agents.
Tying it all together is Azure
unifying the system across cloud
and device.
That's enough of that.
Now let's talk about the
devices.
Today we are previewing two very
broad categories.
The first is stationary and the
second is port able.
The first device is designed for
your desk.
It is built on media tech
silicon.
With hello for business walking
up to the device securely signs
you in giving you direct access
to your agent.
Just like Nathan is about to
show you here.
For the information work this
means frictionless yet protected
access to Microsoft 365 Copilot
grounded in work IQ.
What matters next in your
workday helping you think, plan
and even act by delegating task
to your agent with a simple tap
or just using your voice.
Dedicated Ambian device for
work.
It acts as campaign onto your
existing windows Copilot Plus
-- PC.
Or access windows 365 in a
connected monitor.
How cool is that?
[Applause]
The second is port able.
Re-imagining a wear able
millions of people use every
day.
The access badge.
Built using Qualcomm silicon
wear able this badge is light
weight form factor designed for
agents on the go.
Adapt able across variety of
vert
verticals  and workflows.
I have an early prototype of the
badge.
Using my finger print I tapped
to unlock the device now I have
all of my agents in a secure
manner.
Gather content for social media
post for today.
Why not do it right now.
I am going to hit record and the
device's camera is recording.
Hope you don't mind I am going
to take shots.
Find good shots from this clean
them up and send them for me and
my team to review.
There you have it.
Now my agent is off running
through multiple tasks I clean
them up and send them to me and
the team.
Pretty cool.
I know it is a simple demo but
it is all agent driven and there
are so many verticals and
opportunity.
Imagine in healthcare from the
moment you pick up the device
the right agent shapes the
experience around the roll and
the workflow helping with check
ins, patient records and
critical insights.
All through enterprise grade
secure access.
And with the built in
microphones the nurse can start
a hands free voice based
documentation including
dirizezation and and notation.
The side phasing camera can help
with asht vitals or scan
medications or help verify
workflows.
This is a few examples of how
the small purpose built wear
able can bring intelligence
directly into the flow of
patient care helping nurses
access and gather and even act
on information while staying
print with the patient.
Both devices are an expression
of devices the core hardware and
software are designed to be
highly flexible.
With a few changes loading a
different agent adjusting the
shape, screen size, sensors or
input methods the same
foundation, the same software
can be adapted for many
verticals and workflows such as
retail, industrial, hospitality,
financial service, legal and so
forth.
That is the power of the
platform, that flexibility.
Whatever scenario there are
places where computing has not
naturally fit before.
While this is an early look, we
are really excited that ak ue
whether, best buy, target and
others are working towards
exploring how devices can
improve their workflows.
This is the broader opportunity
for the ecosystem.
Agents moving outside of the app
and taking shape in devices
designed for specific scenario,
a specific customer and a
specific place.
For all of you this is the
moment to imagine where your
agent should live, what form
they should take and what new
work they can unlock.
Last week Satya sat down with
Qualcomm, Chrissian yaw to talk
about the future.
>> Incredible to have you at
device lab and talk about the
reference designs.
>> Happy to be here.
I have been to the device lab a
lot recently.
>> One of the things that you
and I have chatted for a while
is how there's a real platform
shift.
We are moving from building
operating systems, devices for
apps for agents.
You want to talk about how you
see this?
>> This is technology this one
seems to be a big one.
Agents change the whole nature
of the device in itself.
Starting with the fact that if
AI understands the world as we
understand it it will be closer
to our senses, closer to our
eyes and mouth and ears.
It will be things we wear.
You need computing which is
geared towards real time
context.
And from silicon to cloud.
>> This is one of the references
we have that I love.
There is stuff happening 07b9
edge here.
Things on the cloud.
You want to talk about the core
systems and silicon implications
for such a new ecosystem.
>> You need a power efficient
CPU.
The silicon is designed for you
to have a cloud native
experience.
You have a lot of sensors for
context.
It is personaized.
It is a thank  change in the
nature of devices.
Wear able platform is changing
itself.
You see incredible factors.
>> The computer platform, how do
you build it such that there is
an open ecosystem.
It is not about one agent it is
about any agent.
>> Because the smartphone today
is at the center of your digital
life, the job of those devices
today is to be extending the
functionality of the smartphone.
You saw many platforms became
vertical.
It is a natural thing to have a
vertical platform from the same
company.
The phone was at the center.
That changes dramatically when
you think about agents.
Agents becomes the center of
your digital experience.
They will be looking for an open
horizontal platform that enable
the agents to be interacting
with the best possible device
for different applications.
>> We want to make it possible
for anybody working with agentic
system not just bound to devices
but imagine they can be many
devices that carry that
intelligence in different
context.
That's the open ecosystem we
want to build together.
It is great to partner with you
to get this started.
>> We are proud of this
partnership and that's just the
beginning.
>> Thank you very much Steven
and Christiano.
>> It is a new platform but it
is a set of new platform rules
that don't in some sense hem in
what you can imagine the type of
form factors where your agents
live.
Where the new platforms come you
get to rewrite even the rules of
how new platforms operate.
That's what we are trying to get
done with project Solara so you
as developers and enterprises
have the flexibility to imagine
the form factors that you want
and have agents be ubiquitous.
Let's go up the stack to the
next layer.
We are building a new
intelligence layer bringing
together the models, context as
well as the tools.
It starts with model choice.
Every customer every developer
is going to choose the right
model for the right task and
eval mix.
Agency budget and foundry today
has over 121 sthou models.
The largest model catalog out
there.
From OpenAI to an thropic.
Even MAI models.
Last week we brought the OpenAI
real time voice models along
with Claude Opus 4.8 to foundry.
We are continuing to bring these
frontier models.
The consideration about the
models is becoming increasingly
key.
The last developer counsel to
now when you are building the
agentic system having this
context really shaped right is
becoming super important.
In fact it starts right at the
data tier.
The data to date has been built
for application that is
supported user facing
applications.
Now you have to change build
them for agents again different
call patterns even to the data
tier.
Agents are restoring,
retrieving, reasoning, acting
and learning.
That is what is happening in a
continuous loop.
They are using Cosmos DB,
ChatGPT does, Azure search
retrieval of ind -- indices.
They started the business logic
tier effectively for agents.
You have fabric real time
intelligence which now brings me
to an exciting new service
Verizon DB which is fully
managed SQL server on Azure.
One of the things we wanted to
make sure we built ground up
Proest gres managed service for
higher availability scaleout.
It is automated fill over 128
terra bites per cluster.
The read heavy workloads.
You can scale with this managed
service.
In our internal testing we are
seeing Verizon is having 3X
through put compared to
PostgreSQL.
It is critical thinking about
the scale you need.
The other data workload we are
changing dramatically is the
data warehouse in a world where
agents are constantly querying
data, data warehouse is
critical.
One thing to have it mission
critical for users but when
agents need analysis done on the
fly bringing GPU acceleration to
fabric is super key.
We are seeing 7X performance
gain.
It is thrilling to see that AI
acceleration.
[Applause]
So if you sort of have the data
tier, the layer about this is
the IQ layer that we are
building that brings together
essentially the model
capabilities to -- along with
the data.
You kind of mix the data and
model capability so you can
deliver that right context to
unlock intelligence.
In fact when people talk about
token efficiency this is perhaps
the most important
consideration.
If you structure the context
right and feed the models you
are by definition going to be so
much more token efficient.
The first domain is the web.
Web grounding is so important.
You need that fresh, high
quality and fast web data.
And that's why we are really,
really excited to announce today
web IQ.
[Applause]
And web IQ is built on our
global infrastructure that is
already serving over a billion
users.
But fundamentally rearchitected
for the LLM and agentic
workflow.
It is model agnostic, MCP
native.
Plugs into any agent run time.
It has web and news, images,
video, so agents can ground
responses in flesh, verify able
content, and web IQ leads across
all of the three key criteria.
It is best in class in quality,
best in class in speed as well
as in cost.
So we are very, very thrilled
about web IQ being in the
developer's hands as you build
out agentic systems.
We are not stopping beyond the
web.
Every developer wants to ground
their agents on what is the most
valuable data across the
enterprise.
We are bringing together
foundry, fabric and Microsoft
365 as this unified IQ layer.
Continuously updated
understanding of your
organization to show you all of
this rich IQ in action building
real life agents here is Elijah.
Elijah take it away.
[Applause]
>> Agents are only as good as
the context we give them.
Microsoft IQ unifies enterprise
intelligence for every
organization.
I am here at a power utilities
control center and will start by
running a long running agent.
This agent is going to help us
assess the current grid
operations incident and produce
a brief for us so we can respond
accordingly.
Now I am going to go ahead and
kick that off.
While that runs let me show you
how we got here.
We built our agent
And its also wired to a Foundry
IQ knowledge base.
A single grounded source that
packages our documents,
operational data, and people
into context the agent can
reason over.
After building the agent in
Foundry, we published it to
Microsoft 365 for the whole
team.
Let's go see it in action.
Now, here in M365, I will start
with a question about current
events that an ungrounded LLM
wouldn't be able to answer.
I'm going to ask about current
electricity prices in SF.
Our agents pulls in the first IQ
tool, Web IQ, search built for
the AI era.
It delivers industry-leading
quality, velocity, and
efficiency.
Web IQ constantly indexes fresh
official sources and does a
great job with semantic
documents.
And it give us our answer.
Grounded in reality.
Not only can we deploy our agent
here, but we can embed it.
Let's head back to the control
center.
Let's how we handleeds a
previous incident.
Can he asked for --
Deasked for details at our at
risk substations.
The power of Microsoft IQ comes
when we combine that external
knowledge with our own internal
enterprise context.
For this information our agent
pulls in the next layer, Fabric
IQ.
Here is bright line's grid
represented as a tab Rick on
theology, an operational of the
live grid, and we didn't build
this from scratch.
It takes models used by millions
of customers and lets teams
extend them into rich ontologies
that helps run the business.
This model -- yes!
This model is coupled with live
telemetry, so it reflects the
real operational state of the
grid minute by minute.
This is what Microsoft IQ means
by enterprise intelligence.
[Applause]
Not data scattered across
disparate systems, but a single
living model of the business
that an agent can reason over.
Now, turning back to our agent.
We can see that it gave us a
table of our most exposed
substations.
That's the agent query and the
ontology you just saw.
Now the agent has access to the
outside world and our COMBRID.
The last -- and our grid.
The last piece turns the
situation into a response.
Our policies and our people.
By asking, "What are the steps
to respond to a substation
trip," we activate the final
layer, Work IQ.
This is Brightline's response
procedure in SharePoint.
It's the play book the team
reaches for when something goes
wrong.
And the important thing, the
agent isn't working from a stale
upload or copied snapshot.
It's answering from the same
source the team maintains day to
day.
When the procedure changes, the
answer changes with it.
No reuploads.
No prompt rebuildings.
And no stale versions.
And critically, this is your
knowledge.
The assets you create stay with
you, no matter what model or
agent is reasoning over them.
Now, if we return to our agent,
we can see the proper way to
respond to this issue.
Not a generic recommendation,
but our play book applied to
this incident.
Now, we just saw one situation,
three questions, and one
connected answer.
Now let's go check back in on
our long-running agent.
And ...  oh!
Let's check the backup really
quick.
Moment of truth.
And ...
Boom!
Our task finished!
Ha-ha!
[Applause]
Here we can see every step the
agent took.
First, beginning with Web IQ,
connecting it on the outside
world.
Second, fabric IQ through
foundry, organicing it in the
is -- anchoring it in the state
of operations.
And work IQ, grounding in people
and procedures.
I triggered this manually, but
with Foundry routines, this can
run on a schedule, turning a one
off response into continuous,
proactive execution.
And if we look closely, we can
see it even use the power of
work IQ to alert me directly
about the incident.
And if we go ahead and check
Teams, it sent me a brief
notifying me of the situation.
[Applause]
That's the power of Microsoft
IQ.
When the crisis its, teams don't
chance answer.
They get an answer all in one
place they can trust.
Back to you, Satya.
[Applause]
>> All right.
Thank you, Elijah.
And now, you know, let's move up
from this context model layer to
deploying these agents and
thinking about the run time.
And, you know, when you're
building a first-class agentic
system, you need a first-class
agent run time and a platform
that we are going to ship both
with Windows as well as part of
Foundry in Azure.
We want Windows to be a
fantastic place to run and scale
agents, and agents effectively
are a new execution environment.
Right?  It's a new paradigm,
even.
They reason continuously.
They generate and run code
dynamically.
They take action across files
and devices, as well as across
the network.
Obviously there's a lot of power
in it.
Right?
The fact that it can generate
code and act on it, on a
long-running agent that's
autonomous.
But obviously it creates new
risk.
And that's why today we're
introducing Microsoft execution
containers, or MXC, which is a
new policy layer that lets
Windows apply isolation and
containment, using AI native --
OS native primitives.
You need to bake this into the
operating system, so that the
containment is enforced by
policy.
You can have process level
isolation for lightweight agent
actions.
You can have session-level
isolation for user separation.
So Windows and Linux machines,
including WSL, for much stronger
boundaries.
And in fact, if you want full
isolation and containment,
Windows 365 for agents, for
maximum isolation in a separate
managed environment,
effectively.
You can pick the right
containment option for the work
load, and windows will enforce
it.
And I think this becomes pretty
critical as you think about
deploying agents at scale on
your Windows desktop.
We want to ensure containment is
enforced, of course, regardless
of who builds the agent.
This is why you want to bake it
into the operating system.
On to that end we're working
with many partners to ensure
that taint, we're supporting
real developer workloads out
there and addresses the needs.
And NVIDIA is bring Open Shell
so Windows, and today, we are
really thrilled to announce that
Open Claw redundancy on Windows
leveraging MXC.
[Applause]
We are very deeply engaged with
the team to make Open Claw run
super well on Windows.
Let me hand it over to my
colleagues scat and Samantha
toish -- Scott and smoothened to
show you.
Scott and Samantha?
[Cheers and applause.]
>> Hey, friends!
Open Claw came out in November
of last year, and it took the
world by on the stomach.
And for the -- by the storm.
And I've been using it to stay
on top of my health.
It can help me manage my blood
sugar and gives me
notifications.
I've got line triaging email,
GitHub issues, and buys movie
tickets.
What are you using your for?
>> I turned my Open Claw agent
into my triathlon coach.
It developed a work back plan
for me, using my data to  notify
me how I'm progressing and
keeping me accountable.
>> We're working closely with
Open Claw to make them
successful and more successful
on Windows.
We've collaborated on GitHub to
bring you an Open Claw app.
It will help you set up your own
on or connect to existing ones.
And the Windows companion, we're
going to sandbox the Open Claw
tool calls to keep you and your
system safe.
>> Yeah!
You'll see the Open Claw windows
app rin running in the
background.
Right-click on it, Scott.
>> All right.
>> It looks awesome!
It looks like a native windows
app because it is.
It's got information about I
gateway, other machines, my
sessions, and my usage.
I've also got quick access to
things like chat, Canvas, the
main dashed, and more.
Let's jump into companion
settings.
Within the app, we've got full
chat support with tool calling,
and you'll notice in the corner,
we've got lots of PERMTHSZ
options, along with our sandbox
configuration.
>> Thepermissions
options, along with our sandbox
configuration.
>> The sandbox is interesting
because this is using MXC, and
for this, we're going to be
using process isolation.
Now, newer version of Windows
will have more containment
options, so keep your eyes out
for news.
I've got one-click security
option settings, but Samantha,
talk to me about custom folders.
>> Yeah.
You've got full support about
what files and folders you want
Open Claw to have access to, and
really granular security
features like clipboard access
or talking to the internet
itself.
Now, I've given it read-only
desktop -- read-access to your
depth folder.
Open Claw already has a rich
safety layer, augmented more by
me or policies by IT.
For the purposes of this demo,
I'm going to do something scary
and ask Open Claw to delete all
the fails on your depth -- files
on your depth.
>> I like a clean desktop.
>> You hid all your icons from
the audience while we were on
stage.
I think we need to show the
audience who you really are
>> That's so disrespectful.
I know where everything is.
[Laughter]
It's just -- don't touch my
stuff!
I know where they are.
Sam, I need to make sure that
you're clear that a messy
desktop is an organized mind.
I'm pretty sure that that's
the ...  that's the quote,
right?
So what we've done, asked Open
Claw to delete those files from
the Windows node, and the only
thing that is going to keep it
from happening is MXC because
we've turned off all of the
layers that Open Claw offers,
but our IT, in this case,
Samantha, has stet to
-- you can see the attempts, and
checking the directory, and
deleting again.
It wants the files gone, and I
want them to stay.
[Laughter]
Ope!
No!
The read-only sandbox is there.
94 je pegs are still there.
They're safe!
>> Foiled again!
>> Oh, my goodness.
So bad.
>> We've seen security
sandboxing, and brought together
all in this alpha release of a
Windows companion app.
We think this app is a great
opportunity to showcase Open
Claw on windows, and it's only
going to get better in the
coming months
>> That is right.
And, by the way, I want to note
that we're doing a all this
development work on this calm
Windows development machine with
all the tools that I love, like
WSL, containers, a
containment, and I've even got
GitHub Copilot with multimodel
support ready to go.
This is literally how the team
and I have been working on the
Open Claw app on GitHub.
Now, people wonder how this came
together.
Turns out that over the
holidays, I got a DM from this
random guy on the intent, and it
takes me a couple of days to get
back to him.
And then when I did, we just had
this kind of cool idea.
That maybe he should come to --
to Microsoft Build.
I think there's one more person
that we want to thank for
bringing the next generation of
agents to the world.
Everybody put your hands
together for the claw father
himself, Peter Steinberger!
[Cheers and applause.]
>> Samantha, it's just showing
off my secret DMs!
I'm so excited to see Open Claw
native on Windows.
You know, watching a claw try to
delete all your desktop files
and just fail makes me really
happy.
[Laughter]
Because six months ago, that
totally would've worked.
[Laughter]
I built Open Claw to have access
to everything.
My files, my machines, my chats.
Always on, and fully open
source.
That's what makes it so
powerful!
And that's what also makes
companies a bit nervous.
You know, what I kept hearing
was, "Peter, I love my claw.
Can I use this at work?"  And
that's what we spent the last
few months on.
With Microsoft, git Hick, open
AI, NVIDIA, just to name a few.
We had observability, auto mode
for permissions.
We changed how access works.
It's not all or nothing anymore.
You can pick which folder should
read only, which ones should be
hidden.
Here's the nutrition:
--
Here's the news: .
You can run it inside your
company now.
[Cheering]
And we even made the harness
itself a plugin.
You can bring your own.
Copilot, codex, whatever you
already trust in  and your rules
come with it.
And you put Open Claw on top of
it.
Persistent memory, heartbeats,
and a claw right inside Slack or
Teams.
It's been really exciting to see
Open Claw grow into something
much bigger.
A global movement.
And a community.
And I started the Open Claw
Foundation, a really nonprofit.
Any model, any operating system.
Because we are entering a new
era of building agents, more
capability for the people who
don't code, and more power for
those who do.
And we get to do this, we get to
build it together in the open.
So my task is simple:  Come
build with us.
Thank you.
[Cheers and applause.]
>> Fantastic.
Thank you very much to Peter, to
Samantha, to the companion app
team for their hard work.
Thank you to the Open Claw
community for giving everyone
here a crucifix  crustacean -- a
crustacean of their own.
And that's the first time you've
even Open Claw running on a
Surface ultra.
[Cheers and applause.]
>> All right.
Thank you very much, Samantha,
Scott, and Peter.
It's so wonderful to see Open
Claw come to Windows.
And have all of that capability
in terms of the security and --
and that comfort, to be able to
have these long running agents
and unmetered intelligence come
together.
So now, let's move from the
Windows side on the edge to the
cloud with Foundry briar briar,
and we're building Foundry into
a full application platform for
the agent era.
Right?
Every era of platform shift,
when you move to the cloud, we
have the cloud stack in Foundry.
We're excited about the Foundry
hosted agent as a runtime for
long running agents.
You know, agents now have -- if
you're building in Foundry
hosted agents, you can have all
the IQ layers.
You have the tools.
You have the durability and the
memory and the state.
You have your own sandbox.
In fact, it's a super-fast
sandbox that you can spin up.
You can generate the rubrics.
You can -- and the evals.
You can in fact have all the
safety and the guardrails around
your agentic system.
And in fact, even one of the
coolest things in Foundry is
it's a continuously improving
loop, even.
It's got that self-improvement
loop built in.
You build an agent that's
continuously getting better.
And I'm really also excited
today to announce a partnership
with Fireworks AI, bringing all
of their open wave models to
Foundry.
That means giving you as
developmenters more choices, as
well as that great inference
stack, to build the next
generation of these agentic
indications, with all the
enterprise Rayls that Foundry
has, as well as the governance
that Foundry has.
Really excited about that
partnership.
[Applause]
And so now that brings us to the
tools.
Data itself is at the heart of
all this.
You know, in fact, Jensen spoke
to this.
GitHub is not just about the
code repo.
It's becoming the control plane
for all the agents.
And nearly everything we measure
on GitHub, whether it's repo
creation, PR activity, API
usage, actions, all of this are
going faster because of the
agentic workflows.
The new scale is driven by
humans and agents collaborating
together.
And they're exposing too long
-- tooling crass every form
factor.
We've seen tremendous growth in
CLI, driven, you know, the
approachability of the CLI form
factor, it's allusion -- always
been great to go to a termal.
And now when combined with
models and natural language, CLI
is the thing that everything
goes to.
But end of the day, when you
have hundreds of CLI's, it
becomes pretty complicated.
It doesn't scale.
Especially the cognitive load
that I have when you have 100CLI
sessions open, is such that you
kind of need something new.
And so that's what has led us to
build -- you know, we need like
this tool, essentially, that has
the speed and the flexibility of
a CLI.
But has the capability of an IE,
and the ability to scale to
infinite number of agent
sessions.
So today we're taking that next
big step, introducing our new
git Hick Copilot app --
Our new GitHub Copilot app.
[Applause]
And we realize it's not
sufficient.
Because you still have a back
toned deal with.
Code is easy to generate, but
what about the back end?
You need to content with
identities, storage, database
schemas, and that's why we're
really super excited about
Rayfin, an agent-first SDK that
connects your agents to the back
end as a service, and we're
bringing this to everywhere you
build.
That's why I'm, again, super
excited about Rayfin and the
relationship with Replit.
You can now build apps in
Replit, while the -- yeah.
[Applause]
You can build the app in Replit
while the app and data are
deployed into the
enterprise-managed fabric
tenant, thanks to the Rayfin
SDK, which is available now for
anyone else to be able to use
with their tools as a back end,
and essentially have the back
end service.
And now to show you all of the
Foundry and Rayfin and building
agents and the long running
agents, let me invite Cassidy.
Take with away.
[Applause]
>> Hello, everyone!
I'm so excited to be amongst my
fellow Devs.
This is a long day.
Fix your shoulders.
Sit back.
I see a lot of you sitting up.
Great.
I know you're drinking from the
fire hose of information today,
so I want you to go into the
next few minutes thinking, "What
can I drywall try out on -- what
can I try out later today?"
First, I can't wait to show you
the new GitHub Copilot app.
This is your home base for
development and operations on
your computer.
And we think you're going to
love it.  Let me show you
around.
When you open up the app, you
see the home screen where you
can kick off a new session.
But before night the serious
stuff, you can drag Mona around,
and there's a game!
Look!
It's so fun!
[Laughter]
I'm not very good at it, so
let's just get back to, you can
kick off a new agentic coding
session.
So I started off one a little
bit earlier here.
And it gave me a review of a
bunch of release blockers.
Which one should I fix?
Call it out.
83?
The critical ones?
You know what?
How about we just do all of
them?
Let's go!
This app will now kick off a
separate session for every
single issue here.
I don't have to worry about
stashing or coding complex or
anything, because the app takes
care of that with Git work
trees, that are isolated
environments for each session.
Your agents can work in parallel
without stepping on each other.
But you still have to merge
them.
Right?
So -- [chuckling] -- Copilot has
your back there too.
If I head over -- not to this
one.
But to this issue here, I can
run agent merge.
And when I enable agent merge,
cofight will baby sit this PR
through CI check, code review,
and merge collects.
Okay.
Let me keep showing you around
while it's running.
If I head over to my work, I can
see a focused view of all of my
activity ask just projects
loaded in the app, PRs,
everything here.
And under automation, I have a
bunch of reusable sessions that
can run locally or on the cloud.
You see there's issue poetry
there.
That's real.
And that is load-bearing.
Okay!
[Chuckling].
And now undersessions, like I
briefly showed earlier, these
are sessions.
If I want to add a new
repository, I can click the
button, and it will pull one,
and if I were to add one, I can
add a session, and this is an
open source -- I can start a
session anywhere and it loads
it.
When I look at a session within
this repository, let me look at
the other one, I get an
integrated browser, there's a
terminal.
And a chat.
I can technology light and --
toggle light and dark mode.
And there's a button, pick and
polish.
I can polish anything in this
app, and it adds it to the chat,
and I can say, hey, I want you
to add reordering to this list.
And it will just work, all
living in there.
I have access to all the most
popular models via my single
GitHub Copilot subscription,
including from open AI, Ann
throw meic, and Google.
And having a model change is
agreed.
Not only can you pick the right
one, but Copilot can request a
rubber duck review.
In this session, I was use use
GPT5.5, but it asked one from
Claude opus 4.8.
All models have blind spots, and
the power of this approach means
I can catch them earlier.
This is all very cool.
But working with AI in 2026
should be more than just chat.
You just saw me scrolling up.
There's so many words here.
[Laughter]
So today, I'm very excited to
show you the concept of a
canvass.
I'm going to own one right
there.
The canvas is how an agent can
build a custom UI to communicate
with you.
What if your AI could see?
Everyone say, demo gods, bless
us.
Let's see if it works.
Here's a fun canvas where, if I
get the camera going, okay.
The agent shows your PRs down
here, and I can toggle it with a
thumbs up or thumbs down.
Let's aapprove it!
Hey!
It's so fun!
And goes deeper.
This is just the beginning of
what you can do.
So again, I kicked off a bunch
of different sessions earlier.
This is a signal box app.
It's 100% agent-build.
It's containerized with a
database back end.
Would you be able to deploy this
to your enterprise with no
questions asked?
Be honest.
No.
Yes.
Exact.
No, but you can with Rayfin, and
that is very, very, exciting.
Let me open up a new terminal.
All I have to do is type "Rayfin
up."
And then, demo gods bless you!
Come on!
It will ...
[Singing] maybe dedeploy!
Blammo!
It happened!
Yes!
And hosted on Microsoft fabric.
I know that's a lot.
With Rayfin, your agents get a
complete enterprise back end, so
you can deploy with confidence
in the way that's best for you.
But this is the key thing to
remember:  This app is not just
another session manager.
Yes, it is.
It managing a lot of sessions.
But session managers just make
it easy to create work, but this
helps you to finish it.  Thank
you very much.
Happy pride.
Back to you, Satya.
[Applause]
>> All right.
Now we're back to IDEs that have
UI.
That sort of -- it's so cool!
[Laughter]
It's come full circle.
Now, let's talk about how you
can observe, govern, and secure
these agents.
Agent 365 is the agent control
plane, agent requires their own
identities, access controls.
Even when they're working on
your behalf, right?  You just
want that work on behalf
identity to be enforced.
So we extended an intraagent
need real-time defense, so we
extended Defender.
Agents require this always-on
data protection and compliance,
so we extended Purview.
And these agents can be hosted
everywhere, AWS, GCP, not just
on Azure.
Or build with any framework.
And today we are announcing a
number of updates, including the
GA of agent 265SDK, and we're
expanding it to your local
agents running on Windows and
elsewhere, and the claws, you
just saw earlier.
And let us take a look at how
all the Agent 365 composes.
Over to you, Amanda.
[Applause]
>> Everyone is building agents,
but that's not the hard part
anymore.
The hard part is intrigue
grating them into your business
and governing them at scale.
Today I will show you how
Foundry makes this easy.
Let's start locally.
I've already built a line graph
agent, and now I will show you
the value Foundry adds.
First, tools.
Agents need tools to get work
done, and with Foundry tool box,
I just add my tools once, and
any agent can consume them
through a single MCP end point.
And because tools essentially,
that means governance does as
well.
I've applied a guard rile that
blocks PII from leaking, and all
I have to do is apply this once,
and all my agents are protected.
Now let's make this agent
enterprise-ready.
To deploy this agent to Foundry,
all I have to do is add this one
block of code, and then I push
my changes and GitHub actions
takes it from there.
Once deployed, I can actually
use this agent in the same
Foundry extension I showed you
earlier.
And let's now test it out.
I'm asking it to track a few
open items, from a standup I had
earlier today.
And what's actually happening
right now, is Foundry is
spinning up a dedicated microVM
just for this session.
And the session even gets its
own persistent file system.
What you're going to see in a
minute here, if I go to the
Files tab to track the open
items, the agent's actually
writing to a file.
Pretty cool, right?
Off the top of my head has
server side traces and evals to
show me exactly what happened on
every run.
But how do I know if my agent's
doing a good job?
That's what Foundry's brand-new
rubric evaluators are for.
One easy command, Foundry reads
my agent and generates the
evaluation criteria for me.
It creates a rubric personalized
just to this agent.
Now let's check out this rubric
in Foundry portal.
Look at these dimensions.
Governance outcome correctness,
prescribed source usage.
I didn't write any of these.
Foundry generated them from
production traces.
And with this rubric, I can
score my agent, and run evals,
but we can do so much more than
that.
That's where Foundry's brand-new
agent optimizer takes over.
Here's how it works.
It tunes four things:  The
model, instructions, tool
descriptions, and scales.
And then it generates improved
candidates and scores each one
using the rubric I just showed
you.
Here, I can view the candidates.
I can see the strategy used.
I can see their scores.
And I can actually view exactly
what changed.
This candidate, for example,
improved its score by updating
the model and the system prompt.
Foundry then makes it super easy
to deploy the best candidate as
a brand-new agent version.
But this is not a one time
thing.
Every run feeds the next eval.
And every eval tells the
optimizer where to improve next.
So your agents now get better
the more they're used.
But now, let's put this agent to
work.
I've published my agent to Teams
and M365 Copilot.
Right now I'm going to ask it to
just catch me up on what I've
missed, because I've been o
offline all morning, but my
agent hasn't.
While it works on that, though,
let me explain what makes this
agent different.
This is an autopilot agent,
which means it has its own
identity and productivity
license.
So it can work across M365 on
its own behalf.
Earlier, you saw me using this
agent by myself.
But shipping of features and new
release takes a whole team.
And that why this agent lives in
our Teams group chat.
Let's check out how it did.
Serums as you didded --
summariesed all updates and call
out features I need to track.
But putting this to work in your
enterprise, governance needs to
come first.
That's why every autopilot agent
requires admin approval to she
can review it and choose who has
the ability to talk to it.
But it doesn'tent there.
An over approval, add minutes
anterior and block -- monitor it
and block it at any time.
But governance can't apply to
just one agent.
Every agent in your organization
needs to be managed with the
same rigor as users, apps, and
devices.
And that's exactly what
Microsoft Agent 365 provides.
So let's zoom out.
Today we saw Foundry accelerate
development, take your agent
from local to enterprise-ready,
and put it to work in M365.
Foundry makes it simple.
You build the agent; we handle
the rest.
Now back to you, Satya!
[Applause]
>> Thank you, Amanda.
You know, what you just saw was
how we're building security for
AI.
But there's also one other
critical aspect, especially, you
know, the news today is all
about, you know, how do you
defend yourself using AI against
attacks that may in fact be
using AI?
Right?
So last month, we announced our
multimodel agentic security
system in dash, an agent harness
for security, essentially, that
we build.
We're bringing together a
hundred agents across the
frontier, and custom models, to
really find these exploitable
bugs better than any single
model does.
In fact, when we Dudebuted this
harness, it was on top of cyber
gym [dog barking]  benchmark --
Jim benchmark.
So look what you can do to
defend against AI attacks.
Over to you, Sarah.
[Applause]
>> Thank you.
We know that security scans can
take a while, so I'm not going
to do one life.
Let me show you the results of
an ender scan I already ran on
my code base.
The system runs as a stand-alone
CLI, but today, I'm using it in
my GitHub Copilot app on my
local dev machine.
The scan is broken down but
vulnerability, demands, and
severity.
And it's also an additional
to -- finding traditional issues
like coding errors and
hard-coated secrets.
It's identifying AI-specific
vulnerabilities in the code
base.
What happened under the hood,
over 100 specialized agents
working together to discover,
debate, and improve exploitable
vulnerabilities end to end.
When the scan finishes, it
generates both a log and an HTML
report that I can give to my
management.
The defender details command
allows me to dig into these
vulnerabilities, and you can see
what it is, where it is in my
code, and the severity to help
me prioritize.
And from here, of course, we are
going to fix it.
Now, using the Defender fix
command, the system will
remediate suggest the fixing
directly in my local dev
environment.
When that's done, I can check
out the diff.
So I have full transparency
about what the harness has done,
and I still have a human in the
loop check.
But of course, everything I've
shown you so far has run
locally.
But I can also create a PR to
plug into my existing workflows
and push up to my repo, and I
can take the output from the
scan and upload it to tools,
like GitHub advanced security,
and manage everything alongside
my other indication security
findings.
I've shown it working on my
code, but let me show you a
vulnerability our security
research teams identified using
MDASH that you can look up
yourself.
So the TL;DR, because this is a
lot to read of this bug, is the
time reads an out of date map of
an object.
Runs off the end.
And then crashes the host.
So this is exactly the kind of
bug that the harness was build
for.
Because the floor spread across
three different parts of the
code base.
So no single file looks wrong on
its own.
They look absolutely fine.
And we can even see here be
probably my favorite part, a
statement from the developers
claiming everything is fine.
This is exactly the sort of
reassurance that fools normal
scanners and single AI models.
But MDASH wasn't fooled.
One team of agents spotted the
suspicious gap.
Another team argue they it in
part.
And a third team build a working
example that actually triggered
the crash.
And it did all of this in open
source code base.
And this is a kind of joined-up
reasoning that previously
required significant manual
security research effort.
This is MDASH helping developers
create secure code from the
start, coming soon to your CLI
and the Microsoft Defender
portal.
Back to you, Satya!
[Applause]
>> Thank you, Sarah.
So that was the stack.
Before, though, we move to, you
know, unpacking more of the
opportunity, I want to do
something different.
I want to introduce two people
whose LinkedIn profiles were
both super impressive and
slightly perplexing.
Under role had says they're
general partners on Mantis.
On the previous role, sold out
Madison Square Garden.
Welcome Alex and Drew from the
Chainsmokers.
[Music]
Thank you so much.
One of the things when my team
came to me and said, hey, we're
going to have Chainsmokers at
Build, I thought maybe that's
what we're calling our new
GitHub Copilot app.
But maybe they're your fans.
But tell me about how you got
into this.
I mean, you're being added for
what -- at it for what, 12-plus
years as investors first, and
you had your firm now for
seven-plus years, and you even
picked what I would have not
thought is the natural place,
which is B2B SaaS.
Give us the back story.
>> I'm sure you guys are
wondering what time line you're
on, where we're at Microsoft
Build, but hey, how are you.
We've been in the Chainsmokers
for 14 years, and you know, when
our music started to take off in
the mid two thousand teens, we
got to play a few events like
this.
And we met a lot of the founders
from the consumer mobile cloud
era of startups.
And they taught us a lot and
give us a front row seat into
what early stage investing was
like.
We fell love with it, had a lot
in common with the founders and
the way they build their
business was the same way that
we thought about starting the
Chainsmokers and breaking
through the noise there.
And we got to participate in a
few of their deals.
And we decided to
institutionalized in 2020 and
start our own fund
>> That's cool.
When you hear about all the AI
stuff and what's happening,
there's a lot going on, even in
your portfolio we were talking
back staining.
Things are changing.
How do you see the opportunity
going forward?
>> I mean, there's so many
vectors you could talk about.
There's the creative output
side --
>> Yep.
>> -- we've been experimenting
with in music.
But always important to have
your authenticity when it comes
to creativity.
But on the invest side, we're
moving from producing outputs to
producing actions.
Which I think presents a very
interesting opportunity to
reimagine the entire
architecture of the way software
enterprise is build.
Instead of humus producing
outputs -- humans producing
outputs, it's machines, and
rethinking the entire space in
that context.
>> It's fantastic to see that.
And maybe to close out, any sort
of -- as artists who have had
great success, when you look at
a founder, what sort of is the
advice you give them when you're
creating, you know, you're
bringing something new, and it's
a creative process.
So what is -- what are you
looking for in founders?
What is it that you're giving
them as advice?
>> Totally.
There really are so many
parallels.
Maybe it seems like that; maybe
it doesn't.
But it's really difficult as
artists to really find, I guess,
what your sound s what's
authentically you.
What you can continue to do over
and over, because with this much
competition, you have to be
moving authentically.
You have to be connected to the
product that you're creating.
And -- 'cause you're going to
have to iteratedate and keep it
going for a long time to lock
into your fan base and make
something special and nearby.
And we try -- and unique.
And we try to advise the same
thing.
>> Are you game for playing for
us this evening for our closest
friends here?
>> We'll be there.
>> 6:00!
6 this evening.
Thank you very much.
[Cheers and applause.]
Thank you, thank you.
We will be right here at 6 p.m.
tonight, and really looking
forward to it.
So that effectively sort of
talks a little bit about the
developer stacks.
So now let's talk about what is
the opportunity for every
company.
Right?
At the end of the day, we are an
institution, an organizational
builders, whether it's AI nave
company, whether it's a SaaS
company, or whether enterprise,
the first thing we want to do is
make sure that as you build
things black --
Build things like plugins or
agents or AI apping, we want
them to be discovered through
the Microsoft ecosystem.
That's job one for us.
That's why we're doing things in
Windows or Microsoft 365 Copilot
or in Teams or GitHub.
We want to structure them that
your applications, agents,
plugins are discovered.
Customers are also building lots
of line of business applications
and agents using Copilot Studio,
and we want to make that all
discoverable again, as part of
the Copilot experience.
And Teams in some sense has
become this destination for
multiplayer, human to agent
interaction.
We want you to be able to find
agents, interact with agents,
right in Teams.
And we are super-charging all of
this.
Copilot continues to evolve very
quickly.
It started first with chat, with
some of the best models, with
great access to Work IQ.
We didn't have the name, but
that's where it started.
Then came Cowork, a new way of
working, and generating the
stunning artifacts, and solve
these multistep problems.
Right?
So you assign a multistep task
to Cowork.
You saw GitHub, which has
continued to evolve as well.
And now, as of, you know, come
summer, you will be bringing
coding to all knowledge work
within one Copilot super app.
Right?
That's going to be really
exciting, to see -- yep!
[Applause]
You will have chat, cowork, and
code all in Copilot.
But today, we're introducing
something completely new.
Autopilots.
When you think of autopilots as
enterprise-grade claws.
These are autonomous,
long-running agents with full
enterprise compliance that run
in your tenant.
Autopilots can have a name,
personality, custom connecters,
context, and memory.
And they're totally new way to
reduce toil and get you back to
what you love, to kick things
off, the the first autopilot
we're introducing is Scout.
Let's take a look.
[Music]
>> All right.
[Applause]
As you can see, Scout works
where you work, joining group
chats and teams, handling
threats in Outlook.
Starting today for those of you
on Copilot Frontier, you can try
out Scout.
And in the coming months, we
will build this out to a
complete digital team of
autopilots, right inside of
Copilot.
Right?
So you can go to the Copilot
app.
Scout is the one that comes by
default.
But you can build more of these
autopilots.
And so that's the future of what
we think of as the Copilot
ecosystem itself.
And so far, we have talked a lot
about what you can do to build
your own agents and how these
agents are discovered and things
like Copilot and Teams and
Windows.
But when you think about what
makes any organization, any
enterprise, any company unique,
it is its Ttacit knowledge that
is continuously compounding
through its operations.
So the key consideration at some
level in an AI age is to ask the
question, "What's the future of
the firm?"
How do you continue to preserve
and compound that tacit
knowledge in the age of AI,
where models can learn anything?
From the data and the
trajectories they see.
To do that, we believe that
every organization, whether it's
an AI native company, a SaaS
company, or an enterprise, will
need to build their own
hill-climbing machine.
It's a system that continuously
improves against your
objectives, your private evals,
compounding your advantage over
time.
Not someone else's.
To deliver on this, we're taking
the next step with Frontier
tuning.
We've been working with many
customers already to help, you
know, really build their own
learning loop.
The environment, the context,
the tools, the ribosomes -- the
rubrics, and even train their
own models.
And today, we're really thrilled
and excited about super charging
that frontier tuning capability
with the innovation that's
coming out of our super
intelligence lab, to tell you
all about this, let me hand it
over to Mustafa.
[Applause]
>> Thank you.
[Music].
Thank you, thank you.
Thank you, good morning,
everybody.
You know, we really are living
in the most remarkable times.
Since I started working in AI,
the computer that we used to
train frontier models has
increased by one trillion-fold.
That is 12 orders of magnitude
of computation in just 15 years.
It's clear that a consistent,
exponential increase in
computation leads to predictable
advances in AI capabilities.
And in the next few years, we're
going to see three more orders
of magnitude of compute apply to
train Frontier models.
Long linear hill climbing is the
norm.
The scaling laws are clearly
holding, and it is a remarkable
time in our industry.
And so in this context, we at
MAI are building towards what we
call humanist superintelligence.
State of the art AI capabilities
that are explicitly designed to
serve people and organizations
and not replace them.
Because the type of AI that we
create really does matter.
We need an AI that places
humanity first.
But always prioritizes human
well-being and human progress.
This is the core philosophy and
modification behind our efforts
at Microsoft, and it shapes
everything that we do.
And as a platform company, our
job and our commitment is to
keep you developers building the
absolute frontier.
So today, we're very excited to
announce a family of seven new
models across image, voice,
transcription, and coding.
[Cheers and applause.]
These are all built with real
attention to detail and a
commitment to making very
practical and efficient tools
that are typed to -- tuned to
just how you work in the real
world.
First up:  MAI image 2.5 and its
flash variant, two super strong
models that deliver a step
change in quality, not -- now at
#2, surpassing the core of
Nanabanana2.
[Applause]
They gave you precise editing
with control and consistency,
flashes here for super efficient
production work loads, while 2.5
gives you that maximum fidelity
and professional grade
performance.
Alive in PowerPoint today,
they're rolling out to One
Drive, and you can access them
on Foundry at a market leading
quality per dollar.
Next, MAI transcribe 1.5.
This is the best transcription
model in the world.
State of the art accuracy across
43 languages, beating out Gemini
and open AI's flagship models.
We've optimized it for real
world use so you can produce
highly accurate triceps, five
times -- transcripts, five times
faster than all rival models.
It's integrated inside of
GitHub, Copilot, dynamic 365
contact center, and available in
Foundry where I'm excited to say
it is the fastest, most
official, and most -- efficient,
and most cost-effective
transcription model of any of
the hyperscalers out there.
[Applause]
So paired with that, we've got
MAI Voice 2.
The latest speech generation.
Beautiful prosody, natural
delivery, fine grained control,
in 15 languages with more to
come.
And voice 2 flash, providing the
best value and speed for ultra
lateliency voice, which is the
giggest thing in 2026.
Next up, text foundation model.
MAI thinking one.
This is the first reasoning
model, and it's exceptionally
strong, and our target use cases
of reasoning and sweet tasks.
It's a 35 billion active
parameter E, meaning it competes
in the medium sized weight
class.
And independent human raters on
surge prefer it in overall
quality side by side versus
sonnet 4.6.
[Cheering]
It's achieved 97% on AMI2025,
the key measure of its
capabilities, but most
importantly, it's now at 53% on
bench pro that places it
alongside opus 4-6, at least on
the toughest coding benchmark
out there.
We're very happy with that.
[Applause]
There's plenty more for us as we
get this into production and
hill climb against real-world
tasks and traffic, but what's
most remarkable about this
model, we think, it has climbed
entirely from the bottom.
And that means that it hasn't
targeted any of the benchmarks
specifically, with zero
distillation.
And to us, this is critical.
It means that the model is
created with an enterprise-grade
clean and commercially licensed
data lineage that means that you
can put it into production in a
very trustworthy way with
complete confidence.
Now, finally, I'm incredibly
excited to announce MAI code 1
flash.
This is our new inference
sufficient coding model tuned
for VS code and GitHub CLI.
51%, despite five billion
parameters.
Close to haiku in terms of size
but cheapner cost, delivering
strong coding performance at
great sufficiencily.
And it's rolling out inside of
VS Code.
[Applause]
Now, alongside distribution on
Foundry and optimization for our
1P products, we're excited to
make our models available on
open router as well as Fireworks
and base ten.
This means for the first time
you will be able to tune the
weights directly yourself in an
ecosystem of your choice.
Now, across this entire family,
safety and security has been
build in from the start.
Voice models come with
protectiontion against
unauthorized cloning.
Everything is water marked from
scratch.
Reduced the reFOOUFLS,
improvedish -- refuseals, and
accomplishing a very detailed
technical report today to give
you a full and transparent
understanding of how we put all
of this together.
One of the things I'm
particularly excited about is
that we have been carefully
codesigning our models with our
own silicon.
That means that we've optimized
MAI thinking one on our very own
myo200 Chip and benchmarked
against the GB2300.
So top of the improvement, we're
seeing a further 1.4X
performance per Watt gain when
we run them on the MIO model end
to end, and that's huge.
As everybody knows, this scale,
every Watt counts.
And silicon and model codesign
is a really key advantage that
we think is going to help keep
everybody here right on the
Frontier with the most efficient
and powerful thinking and coding
agents out there.
And we're excited that these
faster and more efficient MAI
models are coming to the N1X
that Satya mentioned a few
moments ago, and we think that's
going to be able to deliver the
very best performance on mounds
in a new -- on windows in a few
months time.
This is what owning the full end
to end stack looks like.
It lets you customize the MAI
models using our full hill
climbing machine right where you
want it.
And it means that the discipline
and very relentless engineering
that has gone into building our
models is now available to all
of you.
On a platform that you can
trust, working on your behalf,
to create custom agents that you
will control.
So the really big thing, of
course, that's happened in the
last year is these RLEs.
Reinforcement learning
environments.
These unique training gyms for
your AIs.
They create company and
task-specific agents, adapted
only to you, built on MAI
models.
For example, within Microsoft we
use our RLEs combined with MAI
models to climb towards the best
agentic ace uses on Excel.
The model is on par with GPT5.4
on public and private
benchmarks, and being ten times
more efficient on cost.
[Cheering]
Thank -- [chuckling]
And many other earlier adopters
are seeing similar results.
When we've tuned our models on
McKensie's tasks, it delivered
the highest win rate,
outperforming GPT5.5, and
delivering 10X grater efficiency
on cost.
To us, this is the advantage of
very carefully calibrated
frontier tuning.
And importantly, unlike with
some of the other companies,
with  shared model
only you keep benefits from the
hard earned workflows, know how,
knowledge and your own
institutional data.
Only you get to control the
resulting model.
So with us, the RLEs and the
models that you build inside of
them they become your mote.
It marks a new era in AI that we
are all really very excited
about.
Okay.
So now just one final
announcement that I am very
excited about.
We are taking customization and
co creation of our models to the
highest level possible on what I
think offers the most important
application of AI, healthcare.
Today we are very proud to be
announcing we are partnering
with Mayo Clinic for a new
frontier for health and deploy
it in their hospitals and
beyond.
Help me in welcoming to the
stage physician ground breaking
researcher, president and CEO of
the Mayo Clinic Dr. Gianrico
Farrugia.
[Applause]
Thank you for being here.
Everyone recognizes Mayo as the
leading hospital in the world
with incredible track record of
research, innovation and
clinical practice.
Tell us more about what hope to
get collaboration.
>> Mayo Clinic is known for
being able to live up to primary
value the needs of the patient
comes first.
We deliver outstanding
healthcare.
We are ranked number one
healthcare organization in the
world, yet we know most people
in the world will not have
access to Mayo Clinic.
So seven years ago we decided to
create a platform, Mayo Clinic
platform, moving all of
healthcare from a pipeline to a
platform.
With our partners that platform
is in four continents and
reaches about 100 million
people.
It has created the largest, to
our knowledge, longitudal
healthcare center in the world,
multimodal genomics.
We have the opportunity to do
what we do best together which
is create a frontier model for
healthcare.
What it means if you are a
patient, if you are somebody
interested in healthcare, you
can get clinical and logistical
answers to your healthcare.
If your healthcare provider,
your physician it can give you
insight, it can act as your
real-time team member it can
tell you what is likely to
happen next, but it can also
prevent harm and therefore
increase patient safety and give
valuable insights that make the
team better at giving you what
you need most which is better
healthcare.
>> One of the things we are most
excited about is the models are
already pretty incredible about
textbook knowledge.
Read all of the journals and
papers.
What they are looking is
clinical practice and clinical
expertise of your team and
clinicians you developed over
the last many decades.
How do you think you might go
about the clinical practice for
the model and production?
>> The exciting part here is we
each do what we do best.
We can tackle something that
Hazel lewded healthcare for a
long time trusted scalable
solutions.
To do that you need to have the
right data, certainly need to
have the right people, but you
need to have a very patient
focused lens.
Between the two of us we have
all of this together so we can
build this frontier model and
offer safe, secure, trustworthy
and effective healthcare
solutions for all.
>> Number one objective is put
the patient first, deliver high
quality that we can as trusted
as we can and share the world
over.
Excited to share this
partnership.
Can't wait to share more in the
future.
>> Us too.
Thank you.
[Applause]
>> So today marks some very,
very exciting steps that we are
taking on our journey to create
humanist super intelligence at
Microsoft.
We have an incredible roster of
seven new world class models to
keep everybody working at the
absolute frontier.
We are really looking forward to
everybody being able to co
create your own unique agents
adapted to you at your control.
I feel this is a new era in AI.
An era of AI that you control on
your terms.
Let's build it together.
Thank you very much everyone.
Now over to Tanaya to show us
how frontier learning works in
practice.
[Applause]
>> Thanks Mustafa.
With frontier tuning we are
making it possible for you to
create your own enterprise AI,
with the models and the harness
tuned on your data and your
workflows.
Let me show you how you can
build your own health planning
machine.
MAI thinking one is available in
private preview in the foundry
model catalog.
You can go ahead and deploy the
m
model as is or if you want to go
on your health journey click the
fine tune button.
The first thing I will set.
Next I am going to add a greater
and that's it.
I go ahead andee ate a  -- and
create a job.
It has through logs, scores them
and we start the hill climb.
If you want full control over
the training loop let me give
you sneak peak into low level
training API.
You can see I have the MEI
sinking model.
I can also configure my role out
strategy as well as my hyper
parameters to define exactly how
I want my training algorithm to
work.
In fact I can also incorporate
my own RLM by defining the tools
this model interacts with.
You just saw all of the code,
but as M365 customer you never
start from scratch.
Let's hop on to Copilot.
As a part of frontier tuning we
are introducing a new way to
build environments based on your
data and your workflows.
One of our customers land O
lakes one of the largest
businesses in the United States
is using this to perfect that
butter on your moerning --
morning toast.
Let me walk you through their
environment.
The environment has soft skills,
knowledge and tools.
But in the back end we create an
entire origin for your agents to
continuously learn the way that
you work.
Let's look at the butter report
generation here.
These tasks are very complex.
They require many manual steps
and a high degree of precision.
In these tasks almost 80%
accuracy isn't good enough.
To hill climb to higher
accuracy, we are extending the
industry definition of skills to
include Rubriks on what good
looks like.
This is one task.
How do I scale this to qualify
all
all of the tasks in enterprise.
You spend a lot of time in M365
in teams, outlook, word, excel
and PowerPoint.
We use those signals to suggest
skills and rubrics that define
the way you work.
Next you can add your
organizational knowledge for
branding like from OneDrive and
SharePoint.
The environment comes built in
with Microsoft tools and you can
add custom tools to it.
Because these tools tap into
real workflows we simulate
execution so the model can learn
without actually impacting the
live state of your business.
Now my most favorite part, the
science.
By generalizing all of these
learnings into the main model as
well as in the embedding model,
we are able to hill climb for
tasks that require high
accuracy.
And not only this, we are able
to hill climb to more than 90%
accuracy for Land-O-Lakes class
for using the model.
We estimate the model to be 10X
efficient than the baseline
models.
Let's run the task.
This time using this environment
as an entrancing harness.
Usually this task takes a couple
of minutes to run.
In the meantime I will show you
a cashed response.
They have research with multiple
models including a fine tune
model.
What you see here is a summary
that doesn't feel generic, it
feels undoubtedly Land-O-Lakes.
That's not it.
The task holds itself to high
standards.
It continuously retrospect and
evaluate success.
With frontier tuning your agent
continuously improves with
environment on your data
encoding the way you work.
That is what I call frontier
tuning as smooth as butter.
We can't wait to see the
environment you build.
Back to you Satya.
[Applause]
>> Thank you very much.
Thank you for the partnership
here.
What you saw is a pretty
significant shift.
Times come from just consuming
frontier model to fully
participating at the frontier
and frontier ecosystem.
That is the transition.
You can have private evals and
outcomes private RLEs and
traces, your enterprise
knowledge create scaffolding
from models to hill climb.
That will allow you to
differentiate on-line what you
control.
There is a new operating point
at the frontier.
Where you can use a very
effi
efficient reasoning model and
coding model and achieve
frontier because you have done
the hard work to create the RLE
the hill climbing machine that
create the model your hill
traces can make to the frontier.
We think the combination of the
two is a game-changer and how
people think about what does it
mean to operate in the frontier.
What does the token look like
how are you in control what is
the future of the firm those are
the questions and really the
ecosystem that gets built around
as opposed to a few models
hungry for all data.
To close out I want to talk
about the frontiers beyond to
push the frontier what's the
next best thing.
Building the scientific
discovery loop can have perhaps
the biggest societal impact.
Science today is a little too
len
lenient.
You form a hypothesis, you run
an experiment you wait for lab
results and then you begin
again.
What if the scientific method
itself can become more
continuous, more program able.
That's what we are doing with
Microsoft discovery.
Discovery brings together the
models the ACP compute, the
knowledge graphs of all of the
scientific knowledge automated
lab and simulation into one
agentic discovery loop.
I am thrilled to GA and
Microsoft Discovery, to show you
this in action let me invite
David up on the stage.
[Applause]
>> Hello.
I work in the Microsoft
Discovery and quantum team.
Today to recycle this plastic
like this bottle you have to
sled it and melt it.
You cannot use it to make this
bottle again.
It is down cycling.
We are using Microsoft discovery
to advance that research.
Let me show it to you.
This is the Microsoft discovery
app.
It is VS code.
Agentic Discovery has many with
software engineers.
I want to do three things as a
scientist.
I want to write a scientific
paper about this topic.
Instead of melting the plastic I
can use proteins so you can
recycle it again and again.
Second I want to perform the
actual discovery to define this.
Third I want to create a
protocol to test the results in
a real lab.
If you are a developer the steps
will be very familiar to you.
Let's launch it.
This will is discovery engine.
These are specialized agents
always running in the background
following the scientific
methods.
You can see the agents you can
add more.
Microsoft discovery includes a
community of agents, models and
tools across many domains.
You can have officers fair
parties or create your own.
This is still running.
It will be running for a while.
Even hours or days.
It is running simulations
dynamically.
You can see the files created
here.
This one is the research paper
that I was asking for.
Discovery using no less graph
internally.
It is internal knowledge.
This is a critical asset because
it provide compete visibility.
Scientists can be in full
control.
How do you come up with the
plastic.
You need a way to generate the
proteins and identify the most
promising ones.
There is no out of the box agent
for that.
That's okay.
With Microsoft discovery there
is not an agent for the task.
You can create one on the fly
which is pretty cool.
Here is all of the files that it
created.
This one is the YAMMER for the
agent.
Now we need to generate
candidates for the proteins.
That task requires a lot of
compute.
It is integrated with HPC.
You can use it.
You can see the process.
You start with C protein and
created variations by replacing
small segments.
You can see the segments there.
You apply to see if it helps or
not.
This is done millions of times
exploring a huge tree of
proteins.
The result is 80 proteins sent
to the lab for testing.
It is like the software.
Creating a protein is a little
more complicated.
The bacteria create the protein
for me.
So discovery created another
file.
This one here.
This contains the DNA sequences.
I can send them to the lab if I
have a lab I can integrate it
directly with the agent.
Go to proteins and submit to
lab.
This will use a custom agent
that sends instructions for the
lab appointment.
This is very real.
That's an maut m automated lab.
I have it right here.
This is application controlling
the lab.
It has a Copilot interface so
the scientist can interact with
the lab to the science
experiment.
In this case Discovery has
submitted the job.
You can see it right here.
This will take some time.
Let me open a previous run.
There you go.
These are all of the steps that
the agents are doing.
Most of them completely
automated with human
supervision.
How cool is that?
[Applause]
This is bringing the together
the physical and agents in
unified Discovery loop.
This is one example of what
Microsoft Discovery can do.
Industries are using it today to
embrace a new era of scientific
discovery.
Thank you.
[Applause]
Back to you Satya.
>> Thank you so much David.
Talking about scientific
discovery, we are also
continuing to make rapid
progress on our long-term goal
of building a scalable computer.
We announced last year our first
QPU.
We created a new state of matter
that was only theorized 100
years ago.
Proved it out that it exists.
Our vision was to take a
radically different approach to
addressing the fundamental
barriers to building a scalable
quantum machine which is all
about reliability, speed as well
as size.
Since then, we have continued to
make progress across the full
quantum stack with both our
academic and industry partners.
In Q north we will have a
quantum computer powered by atom
computers natural atom computers
with our stack in there.
We are working with algorithmic
and Columbia and Zurich.
We ourselves use this discovery
agentic loop to accelerate the
work in quantum compressing
years of research into this last
year.
Today I am really thrilled to
announce Majorana2.
The resulting cube bits are
reliable and maintaining their
state much longer while other
common approaches deliver a
lifetime of micro seconds.
Majorana 2 provide cubic
lifetime of 20 seconds or up to
even a minute.
Essentially a thousand times
higher than what we were able to
achieve with high  -- my or  --
Majorana 1.
They are enabling complex
quantum computation in that
lifetime.
All of this in the same cubic
form factor of Majorana 1 in one
100th of a millimeter control of
digital.
Which again is a super important
aspect.
Making it all possible to fit a
million of these cube bits in a
chip smaller than a credit card.
It is this combination of the
reliability, the speed, the size
that makes the topological
approach so unique.
With Majorana 1 we had proven
out the foundational physics and
with Majorana 2 we begin the
engineering scale.
[Applause]
Yup.
Ultimately it is never about
tech for tech sake.
It is about tackling those
pressing challenges of people
and planet.
It is also the fundamental point
of this conference.
The question is not about
whether you can build the next
great model or platform even
this quantum machine.
It is the question of how do we
build the frontier ecosystem
together.
Because there are really two
stories people can tell about
this moment.
One is that technology
concentrates power, reduces
human agency and leaves the
society to absorb the
consequences.
The other is that we use this
next wave to unlock opportunity
for developers, scientists,
enterprises in every community.
Our job is to make the second
story true.
That's our North Star for the
frontier ecosystem.
Let's all go build together.
Thank you all very, very much.
>> Thank you.
[Music]
>> Within reach.
Quantum is our most fundamental
physical theorem.
For quantum to deliver real
world impact it has to be both
reliable and scalable.
>> Reaching quantum at scale
will allow us to make a more
direct approach to solving
problems in chemistry.
>> Discovery in life sciences.
>> We bring drugs to market it
opens up millions of
possibilities.
Quantum will change the world.
This change is just beginning to
happen.